so since that might be unfamiliar for a
lot of people why is it that even if
someone is eating healthy food they're
eating kind of raw produce or cooked but
you know fresh produce even organic they
might have less micronutrients and
specifically why is that such a big deal
for minerals well for minerals it's it
can be pretty substantial our soils are
becoming depleted and that's where most
of the the micronutrients of the foods
that we consume are coming from and you
see it and you know we we really focus
on organic foods and we're all excited
about organic foods and the health
components of organic foods but much of
the organic farming can result in even
greater deficiencies in the
micronutrient profiles of foods of the
vegetables because you Nathan can't
think of his last name but he's he's
kind of the big researcher into nitric
oxide I had a conversation with him we
were talking about the nitric oxide
content of kale and beets and things
like that and he had done a study on
organic versus commercially farmed and
found that there was a significant
deficiency in nitrates in the kale that
was organic relative to the commercially
farm because in the commercial farming
they were adding nitrates to the soil
and that's what the plants were using so
we have to understand that it's not just
that the fact that we're eating the
plant but we have to understand that the
the the environment that the plant grows
in is going to be essential in the
micronutrient component that that plant
contains that we essentially get then
we've got the the aspect of glyphosate
with the commercially farmed stuff which
is a heavy metal key later which means
it binds up to metals which are
micronutrients and the minerals and it
will bind them to the point where we
can't absorb them so it will take out
positive cationic micronutrients like
copper zinc selenium those kind of
things will be bound up so that we can't
absorb them and so you've got to look at
the bigger picture of
everything when we're talking about
getting these micronutrients from food
and understand truly what you're getting
and what you're not I think when I first
started studying health and nutrition
the book empty harvest by Bernard Jenson
was one of the first ones that I read
great where he went deep into the
effects of modern agriculture and mono
cropping and etc on soil health and the
decreased microbiome of the soil the
decreased humic and fulvic acid content
as well as decreased trace minerals and
of course that comes through into the
plants you know I for those who've
studied it they know for those who don't
modern agriculture traditional
agriculture typically puts three primary
nutrients into the soil right NPK so the
the critical things potassium nitrogen
phosphorus that the soil absolutely has
to have to grow plants but the other 70
to plus trace minerals and all of the
microbiome and etc that are necessary
are not going in there so it can get
very deficient in that so you just
brought up one of the very few examples
that might be possible of if someone's
doing organic where they are not getting
nitrogen up high enough you might
actually be low in nitrate I'd be super
curious to see the sample size and where
he was sampling fromming on organics
because obviously someone can do organic
where they are not getting nitrogen or
potassium you know or phosphorus up high
enough but in general if they are
turning stuff back over and putting it
back into the soil the likelihood that
things other than those three are much
higher it's gonna be high and I think he
actually sampled from three different
states organic farmers from three
separate states but I don't know what
the use of the farm was or anything like
that so we referred to organic obviously
more nutrients from a more comprehensive
set of fertilizers than three minerals
is one goal but really the much bigger
goal is avoiding the pesticides
herbicides fungicides that they put on I
would buy organic and supplement nitric
oxide any any day wouldn't you oh yeah I
actually take biryu crystals you know as
a supplement to boost my nitric oxide
levels
since we're touching on it in case
people don't know what is the relevance
of nitric oxide nitric oxide is like the
I mean it's it's one of my favorite
nutrients altogether it has three
different really different separate
components you have the the neuronal
nitric oxide which exists predominantly
in the brain and you're dealing with it
working as a neurotransmitter it works
as a free radical scavenger but it can
also swing the other way and and create
these peroxy nitrates if you're not
balanced in keeping it in a really
homeostatic state and then we have the
inducible nitric oxide which has a lot
to do with the health of our immune
function and then we have the
endothelial nitric oxide which is
something that really is a solid
predictor of long-term cardiac risk and
it has to do with our ability to of our
vessels to really be resilient when it
comes to blood pressure changes and
things like that
post ischemic events those kind of
things and as far as the peripheral
nerves go one of the fun things where I
think many people heard about nitric
oxide first is part of its
neurotransmitter role is involved in
transmitting sensations of pleasure so
nitric oxide deficiency and then and
donea commonly go together well and on
top of that people who don't respond to
erectile dysfunction drugs right they
are almost always deficient in nitric
oxides so you boost their nitric oxide a
lot of times they don't need the
erectile dysfunction drugs and those
that aren't responding you give them a
boost of nitric oxide and sure enough
they start responding to the drugs right
we didn't bother selling it but we made
a really fun cocktail with the PDE form
pde5 inhibitors and nitric oxide
boosters not fun stuff oh yeah
to watch the full episode or to
subscribe to the podcast click the link
in the description or
us at neuro hacker.com slash collective
insights
[Music]